Guide to the Mark Dendy Papers, 1981-2013
American Dance Festival Archives
Mark Dendy papers 1981-2013
American Dance Festival Archives
Dendy, Mark
13.73 linear feet
Mark Dendy (b. 1961) is a New York-based choreographer, writer, dancer, and actor. His career spans experimental dance theater, grand scale site specific work, pure movement dance pieces, opera, improvisation, Broadway, off-Broadway, and regional theater. Dendy also founded and served as Artistic Director of two dance companies: Mark Dendy Dance and Theater and Dendy Dancetheater. His work often responds to societal issues, examining diverse themes such as fame, gender, religion, heritage, violence, politics, the media, and values in society. The collection includes newspaper clippings and photocopies, magazines, programs, flyers, large-scale posters, publicity materials, project files, notes and notebooks, financial documentation, and correspondence. Other materials include photographs, negatives, 35 mm slides, DVDs, and VHS, U-matic, Betacam, Betacam-SP, and DVCPRO tapes.
RL.00018
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
Collection is open for research.
In off-site storage; 48 hours advance notice is required for use.
Access to videotapes or DVDs in this collection requires the use of reference copies. To arrange for the creation of reference copies, if none exist, please contact American Dance Festival Archives.
Access to items in the Notebooks subseries requires the permission of Mark Dendy. Please contact the American Dance Festival Archives for more information.
Provenance
The Mark Dendy Papers were received by the American Dance Festival Archives as a gift in 2013.
Biographical Note
Mark Dendy (b. 1961) is a New York-based choreographer, writer, dancer, and actor. His career spans experimental dance theater, grand scale site specific work, pure movement dance pieces, opera, improvisation, Broadway, off-Broadway, and regional theater. Dendy also founded and served as Artistic Director of two dance companies: Mark Dendy Dance and Theater and Dendy Dancetheater. His work often responds to societal issues, examining diverse themes such as fame, gender, religion, heritage, violence, politics, the media, and values in society.
Dendy was born in Weaverville, North Carolina on May 29, 1961. He received his BFA in Dance from the North Carolina School of the Arts and spent four summers as a scholarship student at the American Dance Festival. In 1983 he founded Mark Dendy Dance and Theater (1983-2000), serving as Artistic Director and choreographing numerous works. His company toured internationally and performed at venues such as the Joyce Theater, Lincoln Center, Performance Space 122, the Harkness Dance Center at the 92nd Street Y, SummerStage, La MaMa E.T.C., Symphony Space, the Kennedy Center, and Dance Theater Workshop, as well as at the American Dance Festival and Jacob's Pillow Dance Festival. Dendy has also been commissioned for new work by modern and ballet companies worldwide, most notably by Pacific Northwest Ballet.
Dendy has performed with the companies of Pooh Kaye, Ruby Shang, Pearl Lang, and the Martha Graham Ensemble. He was also a guest artist with Jane Comfort and Company from 1990 to 1994 and again from 2010 to 2011, performing the role of Amanda Wingfield in Faith Healing, Comfort's dance-theater deconstruction of Williams' The Glass Menagerie. Dendy also appeared in Franchesca Page, a 1997 film directed by Kelley Sane.
From 2000 to 2008, Dendy pursued a career in musical theater, working as a choreographer for Broadway productions of Taboo by Boy George (2004) and The Pirate Queen (2006) as well as off-Broadway productions, including Jacques Brel is Alive and Well and Living in Paris (2006) and Andrew Lippa's The Wild Party (2000). Dendy also choreographed for Julie Taymor's production of The Magic Flute at the Metropolitan Opera (2004), a national tour of Pippin (2006), and the Radio City Rockettes production, Carnivale (2002).
In 2008, Dendy formed a new dance company, Dendy Dancetheater. Between 2008 and 2010 he choreographed five site-specific works, including Golden Belt, performed at the American Dance Festival in 2009. He continued to maintain a link to theater, choreographing the New York City Opera's 2012 production of Telemann's Orpheus, directed by Rebecca Taichman.
Dendy has taught at institutions such as the American Dance Festival, University of North Carolina School of the Arts, Juilliard, New York University, Cal Arts, Bates Summer Dance Festival, University of North Carolina Asheville, Duke University, University of Washington, Oklahoma University, and Texas Women's University.
Dendy is the recipient of five NEA Fellowships and has received support from the Jerome Foundation, Harkness Foundation, North Carolina Arts Commission, Massachusetts Arts Council, Choo San Goh Foundation, Phillip Morris, and the New York State Council on the Arts. He received the National Society of Arts and Letters Sustained Achievement Award in 1990, the American Dance Festival Scripps/Humphrey/Weideman/Limon Fellowship for Choreography in 1995, the Tennessee Governor's Award for Outstanding Achievement in the Arts in 1997, the New York Dance and Performance Award (The "Bessie") for Sustained Achievement in 1997, and the Alpert Award in the Arts as well as the Joe A. Callaway Award in 2000. He also received an OBIE Award in 2000 for his choreography for The Wild Party.
Collection Overview
The collection contains the papers of Mark Dendy, generated through his individual work as a performer and choreographer as well as his work as Artistic Director of both Mark Dendy Dance and Theater and Dendy Dancetheater. It contains printed, photographic, and audio-visual materials that document his performances, press appearances, and public relations activities. The collection also holds materials related to Dendy's creative projects in dance and theater, including scripts, rehearsal schedules, casting notes, and costume and set designs. There are a number of notebooks and handwritten notes on loose paper pertaining to creative projects, choreography, his dance companies, and his personal life. A small amount of correspondence and financial documentation is also contained in the collection.
Materials in the collection include paper-based records, notebooks, newspaper clippings and photocopies, magazines, programs, flyers, press kits, and large-scale posters. Other formats include photographs, negatives, 35 mm slides, DVDs, and VHS, U-matic, Betacam, Betacam-SP, and DVCPRO tapes.
Collection Arrangement
Arranged into seven series: Printed Materials, Projects and Related Materials, Handwritten Notes, Finance, Correspondence, Photography, and Moving Images.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Dendy, Mark; Mark Dendy Dance and Theater; Dendy Dancetheater; Modern dance -- United States; Choreographers -- United States; Musical theater -- United States
Detailed Description of Collection
- Printed Materials, 1981-2013 and undated, (1 box; 39 folders)
  The Printed Materials series consists of performance programs, flyers, mailings, posters, magazines, newspaper and magazine clippings, photocopies of clippings, a publicity report, press releases, press kit materials, full press kits, a costume design portfolio, a postcard, and several folders.
  The series is divided into five subseries: Advertising, Ephemera, Press, Programs, and Public Relations.
  - Advertising, 1993-2012 and undated, 5 folders (Box 1)
    The Advertising subseries contains flyers and mailings for events featuring Dendy as well as those not explicitly mentioning him or his companies. It also contains a costume design portfolio featuring examples from several of Dendy's pieces.
    - Bobby Pearce: Costume Design Portfolio Highlights, undated (Box 1)
    - Flyers and mailings featuring Dendy, 1997-2011 and undated (Box 1)
    - Flyers and mailings, 2010-2012 and undated (Box 1)
    - Pacific Northwest Ballet mailing (oversize), 1993 (Box 11)
    - Posters featuring Dendy (oversize), 2010 (Box 11)
  - Ephemera, 1981, 2011, and undated, 3 folders
    The Ephemera subseries contains folders from dance companies and festivals, a postcard, and an event badge.
    - Badge belonging to Stephen Donovan for Charles L. Reinhart's 80th Birthday, 2011 (Box 11)
    - Folders, undated (Box 1)
    - Postcard, 1981 (Box 1)
  - Press, 1985-2012 and undated, 22 folders
    Arranged alphabetically by material type and date.
    The Press subseries is primarily comprised of newspaper and magazine clippings of articles and performance reviews, the bulk of which are from 1990 to 2000. While there are some original newspaper and magazine clippings, the majority of the press materials are photocopies. Other materials include a publicity report, press releases, and several complete magazines.
    - Magazines, 1998-2000 (Box 1)
    - Magazines, 2004-2012 (Box 1)
    - Original newspaper press clippings, 1993-2008 (Box 1)
    - Original newspaper and magazine press clippings (oversize), 1994-2008 (Box 11)
    - Press clippings, 1985-1989 (Box 1)
    - Press clippings, 1990 (2 folders) (Box 1)
    - Press clippings, 1991 (Box 1)
    - Press clippings, 1992 (Box 1)
    - Press clippings, 1993 (Box 1)
    - Press clippings, 1994 (Box 1)
    - Press clippings, 1995 (Box 1)
    - Press clippings, 1996 (Box 1)
    - Press clippings, 1997 (Box 1)
    - Press clippings, 1998 (2 folders) (Box 1)
    - Press clippings, 2000 (Box 1)
    - Press clippings, 2001 (Box 1)
    - Press clippings, 2002-2012 (Box 1)
    - Press clippings, undated (Box 1)
    - Press releases, 1989, 2004 (Box 1)
    - Publicity Report for Altogether Different, 1998 (Box 1)
  - Programs, 1990-2013 and undated, 3 folders
    The Programs subseries contains performance programs as well as program drafts and edits.
    - American Dance Festival programs, 1994-2011 (Box 1)
    - Programs, 1995-2013 and undated (Box 1)
    - Program drafts, 1990-2009 and undated (Box 1)
  - Public Relations, 1989, 2000, and undated, 6 folders
    The Public Relations subseries contains publicity materials pertaining to Mark Dendy and his companies. Materials include a commissioned essay, company newsletters, artist representation information, full press kits, and press kit materials such as biographies, curricula vitae with choreography and performance history, current repertory listings, compiled press quotes, and company letterhead.
    - Artist Notes, 2000 (Box 1)
      Commissioned essay by Suzanne Carbonneau for Dendy Dance and Theater's Summer 2000 residency at the Bates Dance Festival in Lewiston, Maine
    - Dendy Dance & Theater Company News, 2000 (Box 1)
    - Pentacle artist representation, 1989 and undated (Box 1)
    - Press kits, undated (2 folders) (Box 1)
    - Press kit materials, 1998, 2008, undated (Box 1)
- Projects and Related Materials, 1991-2008 and undated, 20 folders
  Arranged alphabetically.
  Materials in the Projects and Related Materials series include scripts, casting notes, song lyrics, maps, set design photocopies, costume design photocopies, a map, a religious booklet, clip art, and administrative information such as rehearsal schedules and residency information.
  - A Dendy Map of Soho, undated (Box 2)
  - American Dance Festival, 2008 (Box 2)
    Site visit notes
  - Andru's Head, 2004 and undated (Box 2)
    Rehearsal schedules, contact information, correspondence, and press release copy
  - Andru's Head, undated (Box 2)
    Scene breakdowns and script drafts with edits
  - Bat Out of Hell 2100: An Extended Treatment by Jim Steinman, undated (Box 2)
    Bound script
  - Carnivale, 2002 (Box 2)
    Carnivale story outline and contact list
  - Carnivale costume designs, undated (Box 2)
  - Carnivale set designs, undated (Box 2)
  - Clip art (oversize), undated (Box 11)
  - Costume design research, undated (Box 2)
  - Costume designs, undated (Box 2)
  - Glenwood Springs Dance Festival, 1996 and undated (Box 2)
    Calendar, map, and rehearsal schedule
  - House of Flowers: A Musical Play by Truman Capote and Harold Arlen, Adapted by Charles Busch and Kenneth Elliot, 2002 and undated (Box 2)
    Incomplete script draft and photocopies
  - Human Sexuality and the Christian Faith, 1991 (Box 2)
    Photocopy of a booklet published by the Evangelical Lutheran Church in America
  - Mark Dendy Rehearsal Schedules, 2000-2001 (Box 2)
  - Pacific Northwest Ballet, 1994 and undated (Box 2)
    PNB folder containing a map, school pamphlet, and correspondence
  - Pippin, 2006 (Box 2)
    Casting notes and rehearsal schedules
  - The Pirate Queen casting notes, 2006 (Box 2)
  - Project Files, undated (Box 2)
    Mixed project materials
  - Set design sketches, undated (Box 2)
- Handwritten Notes, circa 1995-2011 and undated, (3 boxes; 71 folders)
  The Handwritten Notes series is arranged into two subseries: Notebooks and Loose Notes.
  - Notebooks, circa 1995-2011 and undated, 66 folders (Box 3)
    Viewing of materials in the Notebooks subseries requires the permission of Mark Dendy. Please contact the American Dance Festival Archives for more information.
    Arranged chronologically.
    The notebooks contain a variety of day-to-day information, including personal journal entries, "to-do" lists, choreography notes, sketches, financial notes, and contact information such as names and phone numbers. There are occasionally loose papers with notes or correspondence found between pages or in the pockets of the notebooks. This subseries also includes one dated personal journal entry that is not attached to a notebook. The majority of the notebooks have at least one entry with a complete date, allowing them to be arranged in an approximate chronological order.
    - Notebook, circa June 1995 (Box 3)
    - Notebook, circa May 1997 (Box 3)
    - Notebook, circa May-June 1997 (Box 3)
    - Notebook, circa September 1997 (Box 3)
    - Notebook, circa October 1997 (Box 3)
    - Notebook, circa October-November 1997 (Box 3)
    - Notebook, circa September-November 1998 (Box 3)
    - Notebook, circa November 1998-January 1999 (Box 3)
    - Notebook, circa January-October 1999 (Box 3)
    - Notebook, circa March-September 1999 (Box 3)
    - Notebook, circa June-September 1999 (Box 3)
    - Notebook, circa September-November 1999 (Box 3)
    - Notebook, circa November 1999-March 2000 (Box 3)
    - Notebook, circa January 2000 (Box 3)
    - Notebook, circa March-April 2000 (Box 3)
    - Notebook, circa May 2000 (Box 3)
    - Notebook, circa August 2000 (Box 3)
    - Notebook, circa September-October 2000 (Box 3)
    - Notebook, circa January 2001 (Box 4)
    - Notebook, circa March-May 2001 (Box 4)
    - Notebook, circa July-August 2001 (Box 4)
    - Notebook, circa July-August 2002 (Box 4)
    - Notebook, circa August-October 2002 (2 folders) (Box 4)
    - Notebook, circa October 2002-September 2003 (Box 4)
    - Notebook, circa November-December 2002 (Box 4)
    - Notebook, circa November 2002-February 2003 (Box 4)
    - Notebook, circa February-April 2003 (Box 4)
    - Notebook, circa February-June 2003 (Box 4)
    - Notebook, circa March-April 2003 (Box 4)
    - Notebook, circa April-June 2003 (Box 4)
    - Notebook, circa July-September 2003 (Box 4)
    - Notebook, circa November-December 2003 (Box 4)
    - Notebook, circa March-May 2004 (Box 4)
    - Notebook, circa May 2004 (Box 4)
    - Notebook, circa 2005 (2 folders) (Box 4)
    - Notebook, circa March-May 2008 (Box 4)
    - Notebook, circa March-June 2008 (Box 4)
    - Notebook, circa May-June 2008 (Box 4)
    - Notebook, circa June 2008 (Box 4)
    - Notebook, circa January-April 2009 (Box 4)
    - Notebook, circa January 2009-January 2010 (Box 4)
    - Dated journal entry, March 2009 (Box 4)
    - Notebook, circa May-July 2009 (Box 5)
    - Notebook, circa July 2009 (Box 5)
    - Notebook, circa March-August 2010 (Box 5)
    - Notebook, circa July-August 2010 (Box 5)
    - Notebook, circa May 2011 (Box 5)
    - Notebook, undated (17 folders) (Box 5)
  - Loose Notes, undated, 5 folders
    The notes on loose paper are undated and grouped in the order in which they were found. They contain notes and sketches pertaining to creative projects, choreography, and day-to-day activities.
    - Notes, undated (5 folders) (Box 5)
- Finance, 1983-2005 and undated, 2 folders
  The Finance series of the Mark Dendy Papers consists of budgets, faxes, receipts, telephone bills, tax and budget information for the Foundation for Independent Artists, and a letter to Pew Charitable Trusts.
  - Financial documentation, 1983, 1998, and undated (Box 1)
    Mixed financial records originally filed together. Includes budgets, handwritten notes, IRS correspondence, and records pertaining to the Foundation for Independent Artists and Pew Charitable Trusts.
  - Financial documentation, 1992-1998, 2005 (Box 1)
    Mixed financial records, including receipts, bills, and budgets.
- Correspondence, 1993-1995, 2011, and undated, 1 folder
  The Correspondence series of the Mark Dendy Papers consists of a small amount of professional and personal correspondence.
  - Correspondence, 1993-1995, 2011, and undated (Box 1)
- Photography, 2000, 2004, and undated, 29 folders
  The Photography series is arranged into five subseries: Prints, Contact Sheets, Negatives, Slides, and Photograph Keys.
  - Prints, 2004, and undated, 20 folders (Box 2)
    Folder titles identify either the title of the dance depicted or the type of photograph. When known, the photographer's name appears in parentheses.
    - Beat (Steve Needham), undated (Box 2)
    - Busride to Heaven (Rebecca Lesher), undated (Box 2)
    - Busride to Heaven, undated (2 folders) (Box 2)
    - Classic Sweet (Peter Smith), undated (Box 2)
    - I'm Going to my Room to be Cool Now, and I Don't Want to be Disturbed (Peter Smith), undated (Box 2)
    - Portrait (Lois Greenfield), undated (Box 2)
    - Portrait (Peggy Jarrell Kaplan), undated (Box 2)
    - Portrait (Fredric Lehrman), undated (Box 2)
    - Portraits (Benjamin Franklin Smith), undated (Box 2)
    - Portrait (Michael Wakefield), undated (Box 2)
    - Portraits, Dendy Dance (Benjamin Franklin Smith), undated (Box 2)
    - Portrait, Dendy Dance & Performance (Michael Wakefield), undated (Box 2)
    - Portraits, undated (Box 2)
    - Portraits, Dendy Dance, undated (Box 2)
    - Rock (Tom Brazil), undated (Box 2)
    - Snapshots, undated (Box 2)
    - Technical Photos: The Metropolitan Opera Magic Flute Model Photographs, 2004 (Box 2)
    - Unidentified performances (Fredric Lehrman, Carol Rosegg, Rebecca Lesher, Dona Ann McAdams, Tom Brazil, unknown), undated (Box 2)
    - Worlds Apart, undated (Box 2)
  - Contact Sheets, undated, 1 folder
    - Contact Sheets (MJ Sharp, unknown), undated
  - Negatives, undated, 2 folders
    The Negatives subseries contains 2 1/4, 4 x 5, and 8 x 10 negatives, most of which are copy negatives. It includes some negatives corresponding to prints found in the Prints subseries.
    - Portraits, undated
    - Performances, undated
  - Slides, 2000 and undated, 5 folders
    The Slides subseries contains 35 mm slides, slide film, and scanned slides printed on computer paper. Folder titles identify the title of the dance and the name of the photographer in parentheses, when known. Folders contain slides unless otherwise noted.
    - Classic Sweet (Michael Wakefield), undated
    - I'm Going to my Room to be Cool Now, and I Don't Want to be Disturbed (Phyllis Graber Jenson), 2000 and undated
    - Scanned slides (Phyllis Graber Jenson, unknown), undated
    - Unidentified portraits and performances, undated
    - Unidentified slide film, undated
  - Photograph Keys, 1 folder
    The Photograph Keys subseries contains lists with photographer and subject information.
    - Photograph key sheets, undated
- Moving Images, 1986-2010 and undated, (5 boxes; 91 items)
  Viewing of these materials requires the use of reference copies. When a reference copy exists, it is noted in the finding aid. Originals are restricted.
  Materials with known dates are arranged chronologically. Undated materials follow, arranged alphabetically by title.
  Materials in the Moving Images series consist of DVDs, VHS, U-matic, Betacam, Betacam-SP, and DVCPRO tapes. Original item labels on the videotapes and DVDs are transcribed here.
  - Chant, Hush, Requiem, Beat, Mark Dendy & Company, October 11, 1986, Tape I of II, videotape (U-matic) (Box 6)
  - Reel, Mark Dendy & Company, October 11, 1986, Tape II of II, videotape (U-matic) (Box 6)
  - Wave, Tide, Solo, Beat, Mark Dendy & Company, PS 122, November 29, 1987, videotape (U-matic), 27 min. (Box 6)
  - The White Week, Mark Dendy & Company, Jacob's Pillow, August 1988, VHS (Box 7)
  - Face, Chant, The Character of the Happy Warrior, Frieze, Mark Dendy & Company, 14th St. Dance Center, November 20, 1988, Tape I of II, videotape (U-matic), 32 min. (Box 6)
  - Rock, Movements 1 & 2, Beat, Dendy Dance, The Joyce, 1990, VHS (Box 7)
  - Rock, Movements 1 & 2, Beat, Dendy Dance, The Joyce, January 11, 1990, videotape (U-matic), 42 min. (Box 6)
  - Rock, Movements 1 & 2, Beat, Dendy Dance, Joyce Theater, January 11, 1990, VHS, PAL (Box 7)
  - Rock, Movement I & II, Beat, Dendy Dance, Manmade, The Joyce, January 16, 1990, videotape (U-matic), 43:22 min. (Box 6)
  - Drum, Bicuspid, White Wind, Wave, Chopin, Dendy Dance, Danspace Project 1990-91, St. Mark's Church in-the-Bowery, January 26, 1991, Tape I of II, videotape (U-matic), 41:33 min., loss of signal before Wave (Box 6)
  - Pulse, Dendy Dance, Danspace Project 1990-91, St. Mark's Church in-the-Bowery, January 26, 1991, Tape II of II, videotape (U-matic), 24:35 min. (Box 6)
  - Ballet I, Pacific Northwest Ballet, PNB Offstage, Seattle Opera House Rehearsal Hall, April 3, 1991, VHS (Box 7)
    Composer: Wall Matthews, Choreographer: Mark Dendy
  - Ballet 1, Pacific Northwest Ballet, Seattle Opera House, April 3, 1991, 2, VHS (Box 7)
  - Ballet 1, Pacific Northwest Ballet, Seattle Opera House, April 3, 1991, 3, VHS (Box 7)
  - Solo, Beat, Chichester Psalms, Dendy Dance, The Joyce, January 10, 1992, Tape I of II, videotape (U-matic), 39:45 min. (Box 6)
  - Back Back, Ballet I, Dendy Dance, The Joyce, January 10, 1992, Tape II of II, videotape (U-matic), 55:30 min. (Box 6)
  - Reel #1, Dendy Dance, Duke University, July 12, 1992, videotape (U-matic), dub from original betacam tapes #1-3 (Box 8)
  - Reel #2, Dendy Dance, Duke University, July 12, 1992, videotape (U-matic), dub from original betacam tapes #4-5 (Box 8)
  - Busride to Heaven, January 28, 1993, Tape #1, videotape (U-matic) (Box 8)
  - Busride to Heaven, January 28, 1993, Tape #2, videotape (U-matic) (Box 8)
  - Faith Healing, Jane Comfort and Company, PS 122, April 1993, VHS (Box 7)
    Choreography: Jane Comfort, Text: Tennessee Williams, Jane Comfort, Music: Richard Landry, Brooks Williams
  - Busride to Heaven (excerpts), Mark Dendy, Dress Rehearsal, Performance Space 122, September 3, 1993, VHS (Box 7)
  - Busride to Heaven (excerpts), Mark Dendy, Dress Rehearsal, PS 122, September 3, 1993, VHS (Box 7)
  - Busride to Heaven, Mark Dendy, American Dance Festival, July 10, 1994, Tape I of II, Betacam-SP (Box 8)
  - Busride to Heaven, Mark Dendy, American Dance Festival, July 10, 1994, Tape II of II, Betacam-SP (Box 8)
  - Worlds Apart, October 15, 1995, #1, Betacam (Box 8)
  - Worlds Apart, October 15, 1995, #2, Betacam (Box 8)
  - Worlds Apart, October 15, 1995, #3, Betacam (Box 8)
  - Worlds Apart, October 15, 1995, #4, Betacam (Box 8)
  - Worlds Apart, October 15, 1995, #5, Betacam (Box 8)